[
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 1,
        "year": 2010,
        "question": "<p> (a) Define feudalism.</p><p>(b) State any five demerits of feudalism.</p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>(a)</strong> Feudalism was a socio-political and economic system that existed during the middle ages which was based on land ownership between the lords and the serfs.</p><p><strong>(b)</strong>(i) The system weakened the sovereignty of the state, since every lord wielded some political power.</p><p>(ii) There were constant wars among the lords for the search for more territories.</p><p>(iii) The system was exploitative. The slaves/serfs/vassals and peasants were used and dumped.</p><p>(iv) It encouraged injustice. The lord presided over disagreements between himself and the land tenants.</p><p>(v) The system encouraged domination. It produced very powerful lords who controlled and dictated the socio-economic and political lives of the tenants.</p><p>(vi) There was no security of land ownership. The land being worked upon by a peasant or slave could be taken away from him and given to another or the lord could lose it because of war.</p><p>(vii) The system did not encourage personal initiative and creativity. The tenants were not allowed to think out better ways of doing things but made to dance to the dictates of the lords.</p><p>(viii) The system was undemocratic. The tenants were not allowed to choose their leaders.<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 2,
        "year": 2010,
        "question": "<p>In what six ways can a government of a state violate the principle of the Rule of law?</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(i) Manipulation of the constitution to suit the selfish interest of the executive instead of the national interest.</p><p>(ii) Ineffective control of delegated legislation.</p><p>(iii) Interference with the independence of the judiciary.</p><p>(iv) Inability of the legislature to check the excesses of the executive.</p><p>(v) Flouting of decisions of the judiciary by the executive and the legislature.</p><p>(vi) Disrespect for Fundamental Human Rights by government and its agents.</p><p>(vii) Limitation of the rights and freedom of citizens by government during emergency periods.</p><p>(viii) Undue delay of trials of suspects by government.</p><p>(ix) Social and political discrimination by government e.g. religion, ethnicity, gender, etc.</p><p>(x) Misuse of Para-military organizations.</p><p>(xi) Establishment of special tribunals and extra judicial bodies.</p><p>(xii) Failure to give adequate publicity to laws.</p><p>(xiii) By making retrospective legislation or backdated laws.</p><p>(xiv) If accused persons are denied defence lawyers, especially of their own choice.</p><p>(xv) Denial of right of appeal.</p><p>(xvi) Engagement of secret trials of suspects. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 3,
        "year": 2010,
        "question": "<p>(a) What is an absolute majority system?</p><p>(b) Identify any five disadvantages of the system. </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>(a) </strong>The Absolute majority system is an electoral requirement or format by which a candidate has to score more than 50% of the total votes cast before being declared elected.</p><p><strong>(b)</strong> (i) It cannot work very well where most of the voters are illiterate.</p><p>(ii) It is complicated as it involves a lot of calculations and administrative bottlenecks.</p><p>(iii) It is costly or expensive both in time and finance especially when the process of voting is repeated.</p><p>(iv) The result of the election is unnecessarily delayed if a winner could not emerge after the first balloting.</p><p>(v) Voters whose candidates are dropped in the first ballot may not wish to participate in the second ballot, leading to voters apathy.</p><p>(vi) The system tends to weaken other smaller political parties.</p><p>(vii) It encourages electoral malpractice.</p><p>(viii) It can lead to political tension and violence. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 4,
        "year": 2010,
        "question": "<p>(a) Define opinion poll.</p><p>(b) State five factors that make the conduct of public opinion unreliable in West Africa.</p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>(a)</strong> Opinion poll is a scientific method of measuring the wishes/choice of the people on a given social, political and economic issues e.g. popularity of a government or predicting election results.</p><p><strong>(b) </strong>(i) Lack of expertise knowledge by officials conducting the polls.</p><p>(ii) Absence of reliable technology which may produce accurate results.</p><p>(iii) High level of illiteracy and ignorance among the people.</p><p>(iv) Problems of analyzing statistical data.</p><p>(v) Lack of objectivity among respondents.</p><p>(vi) People get scared of being interviewed.</p><p>(vii) Poor communication network.</p><p>(viii) Possibility of manipulating the figures generated or gathered during the exercise.</p><p>(ix) The selection of the sampling may be misleading.</p><p>(x) Respondents may be highly influenced by cultural, religious or traditional sentiments. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 5,
        "year": 2010,
        "question": "<p>(a) Define public corporation.</p><p>(b) Give five reasons for setting up a public corporation in your country.</p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>(a)</strong> A public corporation may be defined as government enterprise set up by an Act of Parliament to provide essential services like electricity, pipe borne-water, etc for the people at moderate prices.</p><p><strong>(b) </strong>(i) To provide essential and basic services for the people. These services include water, electricity, transportation, roads, housing, etc.</p><p>(ii) To provide employment for citizens.</p><p>(iii) To prevent the exploitation of the members of the public by unscrupulous profiteers whose sole aim is to maximize profit.</p><p>(iv) To undertake essential projects requiring huge capital.</p><p>(v) To undertake strategic projects which the government may not want the private businessmen to handle for security reason.</p><p>(vi) Government may also establish public corporation for the purpose of generating revenue.</p><p>(vii) Public corporations may also be established for the purpose of propaganda. Examples are Radio Corporations and the Television Authorities.</p><p>(viii) It enables government to carry out some duties that require quick actions which ministries cannot quickly or effectively carry out because of bureaucracy.</p><p>(ix) To avoid foreign control of the economy.</p><p>(x) To ensure constant supply of social services.</p><p>(xi) To raise the standard of living of the people. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 6,
        "year": 2010,
        "question": "<p> Identify any six roles of traditional rulers in the pre-colonial West Africa. </p>",
        "answer": "<p>(i) They served as a link between the people and their ancestors.</p><p>(ii) They appointed subordinate chiefs.</p><p>(iii) Maintenance of law and order - They mobilized their subjects, especially the able bodied youths to keep law and order.</p><p>(iv) Preservation of native laws and customs. They ensured that the cherished customs and traditions of the people were preserved and promoted.</p><p>(v) Administration of Justice - They interpreted customary norms and conventions and passed judgments.</p><p>(vi) Community development - They mobilized and organized their subjects towards community development.</p><p>(vii) Recruitment of able-bodied men for war in defence of their territories.</p><p>(viii) They performed religious functions.</p><p>(ix) They collected tributes and taxes.</p><p>(x) They allocated community resources e.g. land.</p><p>(xi) They maintained external links with other communities.</p><p>(xii) They made laws, rules and regulations.</p><p>(xiii) They conferred honours on deserving citizens. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 7,
        "year": 2010,
        "question": "<p>(a) Describe the composition of the Executive Council of the 1922 Clifford Constitution.</p><p>(b) Identify any five ways in which the Clifford Constitution was significant to Nigeria.</p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>(a)</strong> The Executive Council of the 1922 Clifford Constitution was composed of ten official members. The. Council was headed by the Governor.</p><p><strong>(b)(</strong>i) It introduced elective principle in which the people of Lagos and Calabar were given suffrage.</p><p>(ii) It led to the springing up of newspapers and magazines like Lagos Daily News, West African Pilot, etc.</p><p>(iii) A new Legislative Council was set up for the Colony and Protectorate of Nigeria.</p><p>(iv) It created a conducive atmosphere for the springing up of political parties and associations e.g. The NNDP in 1923.</p><p>(v) The Constitution increased political awareness on the part of Nigerians.</p><p>(vi) The Constitution inspired nationalist activities towards securing independence.</p><p>(vii) It allowed more Nigerian representatives in the Legislative Council.</p><p>(viii) It opened the door for constitutional reforms and reviews. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 8,
        "year": 2010,
        "question": "<p>Highlight six political changes introduced into the Nigerian political system by the 1954 Constitution.</p>",
        "answer": "<p> (i) Federalism. The Constitution consolidated the federal system of government in the country.</p><p>(ii) Full ministerial responsibilities. Nigerians were made ministers with portfolios.</p><p>(iii) Direct elections. It brought direct elections to the Eastern and Western Legislatures.</p><p>(iv) Premier. Each of the three regions had a premier as the leader of government.</p><p>(v) Regionalization of the civil service and Judiciary.</p><p>(vi) Establishment of the offices of the Speaker and Deputy Speaker in each legislature.</p><p>(vii) It made Governor to become Governor-General and Lieutenant Governors to Governors.</p><p>(viii) Lagos was made a Federal capital territory and no longer part of the Western Region.</p><p>(ix) Southern Cameroon was granted semi-autonomy. .(x) Membership of the central legislature was increased from 149 to 188. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 9,
        "year": 2010,
        "question": "<p>(a) Distinguish between a Secretary of State for the Colonies and a Governor-General in the British Colonial administration.</p><p>(b) Highlight five functions of the Governor-General in the British West Africa shortly after independence. </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>(a)</strong> The Secretary of State for the Colonies was a minister resident in Britain. He was responsible for advising the British government on matters affecting its colonies. A Governor-General on the other hand was not a minister. He was appointed by the Queen of Britain on the advice of the Prime Minister. He was resident in the colony and acted as the Head of State.</p><p><strong>(b)</strong>(i) He was authorized to appoint a Prime Minister.</p><p>(ii) He appointed ministers on the advice of the Prime Minister.</p><p>(iii) He gave his assent to bills passed by Parliament before they became laws.</p><p>(iv) He was empowered to dissolve, prorogue and summon parliament on the advice of the Prime Minister.</p><p>(v) He appointed members of the Public Service Commission and other important government officials on the advice of the Prime Minister.</p><p>(vi) He received credentials from foreign dignitaries accredited to his country.</p><p>(vii) He addressed the parliament during the first Parliamentary session. (Speech from the throne).</p><p>(viii) He performed ceremonial functions.</p><p>(ix) He could dismiss the Prime Minister and cabinet if there was a vote of no-confidence.</p><p>(x) He exercised prerogative of mercy on the advice of the Prime Minister.</p><p>(xi) He was the Commander-in-Chief of the Armed Forces.<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 10,
        "year": 2010,
        "question": "<p> Describe six achievements of the National Party of Nigeria (NPN) between 1979 and 1983. </p>",
        "answer": "<p>(i) The Party won the Presidential elections in 1979 and 1983.</p><p>(ii) The Party won more seats than any other political party into the House of Representatives.</p><p>(iii) Establishment of steel rolling mills e.g. Katsina, Osogbo, ltakpe.</p><p>(iv) The Party won the majority seats into the Senate.</p><p>(v) The Party built a number of housing estates in each state of the federation.</p><p>(vi) The Party established more Federal Secondary Schools throughout Nigeria.</p><p>(vii) The Party controlled seven states out of 19 states of the federation.</p><p>(viii) The Party won at least a seat in all the states Assemblies except Ogun and Lagos. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 11,
        "year": 2010,
        "question": "<p>(a) What is foreign policy of a country?</p><p>(b) State the main objectives of Nigerian foreign policy.</p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>(a)</strong> A foreign policy of a country is the set objectives which a government seeks to achieve through its relations with governments of other countries and international organizations.</p><p><strong>(b)</strong>(i) To develop mutual understanding, friendship and co-operation with the government of other states.</p><p>(ii) Respect the sovereign integrity of states based on the principle of non-interference in the internal affairs of other states.</p><p>(iii) Peaceful resolution of inter-state(s) disputes. (iv) Promotion and protection of national interest. (v) Eradication of colonialism and racism in Africa.</p><p>(vi) To assist other neighbouring countries to solve their internal problems.</p><p>(vii) Promotion of a just world economic order.</p><p>(viii) Defence and promotion of world peace and security.</p><p>(ix) Non-alignment to any power bloc.</p><p>(x) Respect for international laws and treaty obligations. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 12,
        "year": 2010,
        "question": "<p>(a) Describe the composition of the General Assembly of the United Nations Organisation (UNO).</p><p>(b) Highlight four functions of the General Assembly. </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>(a)</strong> The United Nations General Assembly is composed of all member states. Each has five representatives in the Assembly.</p><p><strong>(b)</strong>(i) It deliberates on issues of matters affecting world peace and security.</p><p>(ii) It discusses and approves the annual budget of the UNO.</p><p>(iii) It approves the appointment of the Secretary-General of the UNO.</p><p>(iv) It receives and considers reports from other organs and specialized agencies of the UNO.</p><p>(v) It admits new members into the UNO.</p><p>(vi) It reviews issues that relate to the functions and powers of the other organs of the Organisation.</p><p>(vii) It amends the charter of the UNO.</p><p>(viii) It elects non-permanent members of the security council of the UNO.</p><p>(ix) It suspends or expels any erring member state.</p><p>(x) In conjunction with the security council, it elects members of other organs and agencies of the organisation e.g. I.C.J, ECOSOC, etc.</p><p>(xi) It alerts the security council of any situation likely to endanger international peace and security. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    }
]